RG 041:001, Board of Railroad Commissioners
Connecticut State Library
Board of Railroad Commissioners records
circa 1848-1912, bulk 1854-1911
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Board of Railroad Commissioners
72.75 cubic feet
The Board of Railroad Commissioners came into existence on July 1, 1853. On September 9, 1911 it was succeeded by the Public Utilities Commission.
RG041_001
1932-074, 1972-003, 1983-028, 1986-025, 2011-125
Historical Note
During the first half of the nineteenth century, the General Assembly appointed individual commissioners to monitor Connecticut's early canals, turnpikes, and starting in 1832 its railroads.1 Safety legislation passed after the Norwalk drawbridge disaster of May 6, 1853 called for three general railroad commissioners to monitor all the companies and oversee compliance across the state.2 Each year in July or August, the Board would hold an organizational meeting to elect a chairman and secretary and, in the early years, to assign specific railroads to each commissioner for the reporting of accidents.3 In 1874 the commissioners became the Board of Railroad Commissioners now appointed by the governor with the consent of the Senate.4 Legislation in 1877 further specified that one commissioner be a lawyer and one a civil engineer, both with ten years experience, and the third "a good practical business man."5
In 1884 the General Assembly established the Asylum Street Bridge Commission to plan and supervise the elimination of a dangerous grade crossing in Hartford. It's five members included the three railroad commissioners.6
The Board's mission was to protect the public interest in matters of safety, property rights, and accommodation. Street railways came fully under its jurisdiction by 1901, as electricity turned local horse railroads into an interurban transportation network that rivaled the steam railroads.7 Among its duties, the Board was charged with approving the locations of new lines and certifying them as safe to open; inspecting all the railroads periodically; investigating accidents that involved personal injury; holding hearings in response to petitions and complaints; researching newer safety technologies; and, reporting back to the legislature.
Individuals, municipalities, and railway companies could petition the Board for redress. On receipt of a petition, the commissioners would set a date; give legal notice to the parties concerned; take testimony, under oath if necessary; deliberate and announce their finding; and, hold additional hearings on appeal. Always limited by statute, the Board's powers to order improvements, rather than merely recommend them, evolved over time. Though it had to work through the courts itself and its determinations could be challenged there, the Board's rulings were usually upheld.
By the turn of the century, the increasing numbers of electric, gas, water, telegraph, and telephone companies brought the need for increased regulation and an agency with an expanded scope. On September 9, 1911 the Board of Railroad Commissioners became the new Public Utilities Commission.8
Two of the longest serving Commissioners were George M. Woodruff (1874-1897) and William O. Seymour (1887-1911), who died in office. For a complete list of Commissioners, see the 59th Annual Report of the Railroad Commissioners, 1911, p. 130. Long time clerks were George T. Utley (1874-1893), who died in office, and Henry F. Billings (1893-1930). The Commission maintained an office from August 1871 until November 1878 in Room 67 of the Charter Oak Life Insurance Building, and from November 1878 to September 1911 in Rooms 41 and 43 of the State Capitol.
See also the.
Endnotes
1Resolves and Private Laws, 1832, title 33, section 7, Boston, Norwich and New London R.R. Co.
2Hartford Daily Courant, May 7, 1853, p.2; Public Acts, 1853, chapter 74.
3RG 041:001, series 1, volume 5, p. 1, 144.
4Public Acts, 1874, chapter 77, sections 1, 3.
5Public Acts, 1877, chapter 144, section 2.
6Special Acts and Resolutions, 1884, number 185.
7Public Acts, 1901, chapter 156.
8Public Acts, 1911, chapter 128.
Scope and Content
Series 1. Record Books, 1854-1911, are largely transcriptions of documents and constitute the official record of the Board. Many, but not all, of the original documents can be found in Series 3 and 5.
Series 2. Correspondence, 1869-1911, bulk 1869-1894, consists of original letters to the commissioners, internal Board communications, and copies of outgoing correspondence. Though some correspondence was recorded in the early Series 1 volumes, the actual letters present here begin in 1869.
Series 3. Railroad Papers, circa 1848-1911, bulk 1860-1911 includes original applications for rights of way, notices of hearings, decisions, appeals and withdrawals thereof, examination reports, requests for special trains, reports of accidents and deaths, and some miscellaneous letters.
Series 4. Hearings, 1875-1883, undated, includes books of notes and testimony taken in regard to specific accidents, such as the Tariffville bridge collapse of January 15, 1878. Includes two photographs of the Hartford tunnel that relate to the Hartford
Series 5. Street Railway Papers, 1892-1912, includes original applications for rights of way, notices of hearings, decisions, appeals, withdrawals of appeals and petitions, materials on vestibules and fenders to improve safety.
Series 6. Asylum Street Bridge Commission, 1884-1892, includes minutes of meetings, correspondence, and hearings records.
Series 7. Miscellaneous Records, 1871-1909, undated, contains two inspection notebooks, 1878-1881 and 1909; a Board of Railroad Commissioners leather pouch; a name and address book, undated; and an unidentified index, undated.
Series 8. Scrapbooks, 1879-1909, contain articles clipped out of newspapers and periodicals, mostly from Connecticut.
Series 9. Accident Reports, 1893-1911, contain reports, either in the form of correspondence or on official forms provided by the Board, by railway companies to the Board. These are not investigation reports.
Series 10. Docket maps, 1870-1912, are of projected rights of way and changes to established lines, grade-crossing elimination plans, blueprints for stations and bridges, both for railroads and street railways.
Series 11. Card File Indexes, are indexes of Board actions recorded in record books volumes 1-41 (Series 1), accidents recorded in record books volumes 1-41 (Series 1), and plans submitted to the Board for review (Series 10).
Series 12. Maps, 1881, 1888-1890, 1893-1905 are maps that accompanied the published reports of the Railroad Commissioners.
Arrangement
Arranged in 12 series as follows:
Series 1, Record books, 1854-1911, are arranged by volume number. Volumes 12, 14-41 are arranged alphabetically by railroad name. Volumes 42-44 for street railways are arranged chronologically.
Series 2, Correspondence, 1869-1911, bulk 1869-1894, is arranged chronologically
Series 3, Railroad Papers, circa 1848-1911, bulk 1860-1911, are arranged alphabetically by railroad and then chronologically therein. The reverse of each document is noted with the volume in Series 1 in which the document was recorded.
Series 4. Hearings, 1875-1883, is arranged chronologically.
Series 5. Street Railway Papers, 1892-1912, are arranged alphabetically by railway name and then chronologically therein. The reverse of each document is noted with the volume in Series 1 in which the document was recorded.
Series 6. Asylum Street Bridge Commission, 1884-1892, documents are arranged chronologically.
Series 7. Miscellaneous Records, 1871-1909, undated
Series 8. Scrapbooks, 1879-1909, are arranged chronologically.
Series 9. Accident Reports, 1893-1911, are arranged by railroad and division and then chronologically therein.
Series 10. Docket Maps, 1870-1912, are are arranged numerically.
Series 11. Card File Indexes
Series 12. Maps, 1881, 1888-1890, 1893-1905, are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
, Connecticut State Library.
Contains charters, petitions, and reports dealing with railroads.
RG 006, Office of the Secretary of the State Records, Connecticut State Library. Railroad mortgage deeds, 1849-1980, articles of incorporation, 1837-1945, and railroad maps, circa 1874-1910. Some maps were placed into the manuscript map collection. Researchers should check the map card catalog in the History & Genealogy reading room.
Note: Connecticut General Statutes require that the Secretary of the State of Connecticut records all railroad company incorporations and all railroad company transactions with regard to the issuance of bonds secured by a mortgage deed, leasing of railroad company property, the acquisition, consolidation, or merger of railroad companies, and liens on railroad company property. Contact the Office of the Secretary of the State for further information on records that might be held there.
, Connecticut State Library.
This is the successor agency to the Board of Railroad Commissioners.
, Connecticut State Library.
, Connecticut State Library.
, Connecticut State Library.
This is the single largest repository of historical railroad materials in Connecticut.
Included here are scrapbooks that cover some of the gaps in Series 8: 1880 October 20 - 1881 April 11; 1881 April 13 - 1883 December 9; 1887 May 19 - 1887 September 14; 1888 February 15 - 1888 December 14.
Bibliography
State Publications
Board of Railroad Commissioners. Annual Report of the Railroad Commissioners of the State of Connecticut Hartford: Press of the Case, Lockwood & Brainard Co., 1875-[1911].
These reports included the highlights of the year, the reportable accidents, the condition of each company, and a copy of its 'returns' form. Mandated by the legislature in 1853, the latter were sent annually to each railroad and asked more than 150 questions about finances and operations. The elaborate statistical charts based on this information, the proliferation of companies monitored, and the railway laws appended would see these reports become 700-page volumes by 1900.
Some of these reports are online in the.
These reports had state railroad maps inserted into the front cover sleeve, 1876-1912, and street railway maps in end sleeve, 1902-1913. Maps for the years 1881, 1888-1890, and 1893-1905, are found in Series 12. Maps for the years 1894 and 1895 are also in Special Collections and. The map for 1906 is in the History & Genealogy reading room
Books
Baker, George Pierce. The Formation of the New England Railway Systems: A Study of Railroad Combination in the Nineteenth Century. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1937.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Board of Railroad Commissioners; Connecticut. General Railroad Commissioners; Connecticut. Rail Road Commissioners
Subjects:
Connecticut. Board of Railroad Commissioners -- Records and correspondence; Electric railroads -- Connecticut; Electric railroads -- Design and construction-- Connecticut; Railroad accidents -- Connecticut; Railroad stations -- Connecticut; Railroads -- Connecticut; Railroads -- Connecticut -- Maps; Railroads -- Design and construction -- Connecticut; Railroads -- Right of way-- Connecticut; Railroads -- Safety measures -- Connecticut; Street railroads -- Connecticut; Street railroads -- Design and construction -- Connecticut
Places:
Connecticut
Document Types:
Accident reports; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Card files; Correspondence; Maps; Minutes; Pamphlets; Scrapbooks
Restrictions on Access
Series 10, Docket maps, are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis. Access to some of these plans may be restricted due to condition or size. Any restrictions are noted on the listing at the History and Genealogy Reference desk. Some restricted items may be made available to researchers after review by State Archives staff.
Series 12, Maps are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
Series 1, Record book, 1854-1864, unnumbered volume, was donated to the Connecticut State Library by the Connecticut Historical Society on April 27, 2011. (Accession 2011-125)
Series 1, Record books, 1857-1911, volumes 1-44, and separate indexes for volume 1-6, were transferred to the Connecticut State Library in January 1972. It appears that these record books were transferred by the Office of the Attorney General, which may have had custody. (Accession 1972-003)
Most of Series 2, Correspondence, 1869-1911; Series 3, Railroad papers, circa 1848-1911, bulk 1860-1911; and Series 5, Street railway papers, 1889-1911, were brought to the Connecticut State LIbrary in 1932 from a gentleman only identified as Mr. Thompson. Part of this material was received on May 16, 1932. (Accession 1932-074). Two boxes of Railroad Commissioner papers were donated to the Connecticut State Library by the Connecticut Historical Society on December 2, 1983. Upon receipt these 2 boxes were assigned accession 1983-019. They have been combined with accession 1932-074 during processing that began in 2008.
Series 4, Hearings, 1875-1883; Series 6, Asylum St. Bridge Commission, 1884-1892; and Series 7, Miscellaneous Records, 1871-1909, were received with the records books in January 1972. These series were placed into accession 1932-074 during processing that began in 2008.
It is unclear when Series 8, Scrapbooks, 1879-1909, and Series 9, Accident Reports, 1893-1911, came to the Connecticut State Library, although it is likely through Mr. Thompson. These series were placed into accession 1932-074 during processing that began in 2008.
Series 10, Docket maps, 1870-1912, were transferred to the Connecticut State Library from the Dept. of Transportation on July 28, 1986. (Accession 1986-025)
Series 11, Card file indexes were transferred to the Connecticut State Library with the docket maps in 1986. They were included in accession 1932-074 during processing that began in 2008.
Series 12, Maps, 1881, 1888-1890, 1893-1905, were placed in the State Archives on July 28, 1983.
Container List
- Series 1. Record Books, 1854-1911; 11 cubic feet (45 volumes + 6 indexes); 1972-003 except where noted
  On spines: "Records of the Railroad Commissioners"
  Titles and dates below as given on spine, unless otherwise noted.
  Content sometimes varies from spine dates and covers reorganizations under subsequent corporate names.
  The first record book is unnumbered.
  Index to Volume 1-6 are in separate volumes. Volumes 7-44 contain index at front of volume
  The index volumes are unnumbered.
  - Record book of Gen. Railroad Commissioners, 1854-1864; 2011-125
    Unnumbered volume
    Title from label on front cover
  - Records, 1857 June 24 - 1863 February 23 (Volume 1)
    Inscribed on front end leaf: "Accidents 1857-1862 Vol. 0 [with "A" struck out]
    Inscribed on verso of second front end leaf: "Index in separate book (long thin book) marked 'Index to Record Book 0, June 24, 1857 to Nov. 8, 1862'"
  - Index to Volume 1
    On cover: "Index to Record Book 0 June 24th., 1857 to Nov. 8th., 1862"
  - Records, 1859 July 8 - 1862 October 28 (Volume 2)
    Inscribed on top of first page: "Copy of letters sent"
    Book in reverse continues pages 144-195.
  - Index to Volume 2
    On cover: "Index to Record Book 00 July 8th., 1859 to Octo. 28th., 1862."
  - Records, 1862 August 25 - 1866 June 21 (Volume 3)
    Inscribed on front end leaf: "Vol 0.0.0. Accidents 1862 to 1866. B"
  - Index to Volume 3
    On cover: "Index to Record Book 000 From Aug. 25th., 1862 to July 2nd., 1866.
  - Records, 1865 August 15 - 1866 February 7 (Volume 4)
    Inscribed on front end leaf: "Vol. 0.0.0.0. Accidents 1865 to 1866 C"
    Testimony in various accident hearings
  - Index to Volume 4
    On cover: "Index to Record Book 0000 From Aug 15th., 1865 to Feby. 7th., 1866."
  - Records, 1866 July 5 - 1868 May 7 (Volume 5)
    Inscribed on front end leaf: "Vol 0.0.0.0.0. Records 1866 to 1868"
  - Index to Volume 5
    On cover: "Index to Record Book 00000 From July 5th., 1866 to May 7th., 1868."
  - Records, 1866 April 10 - 1870 February 16 (Volume 6)
    "Inscribed on verso of front end leaf: "Vol VI"
    "Inscribed on 2nd front end leaf: "A"
  - Index to Volume 6
    On cover: "Index to Record Book A From May 16th., 1868 to Feby. 5th., 1870."
  - Records, 1869 January 18 - 1872 April 12 (Volume 7)
    "B" on lower spine
  - Records, 1871 January 25 - 1874 June 18 (Volume 8)
    Letters dated August 11, 1873 and March 28, 1874 in Box 51 Folder 10 indicate this volume was known as Volume C.
  - Records, 1874 June 2 - 1911 January 25 (Volume 9)
    Letters dated August 28, 1873 and November 20, 1874 in Box 51 Folder 10 indicate this volume was known as Volume D.
  - Accidents, 1872 January 5 - 1874 August 29 (Volume 10)
    Inscribed on 2nd front end leaf: "(Accidents)/(Railroad Commissioners)"
  - Miscellaneous roads, 1880 October 26 - 1891 June 30 (Volume 11)
    Includes projected, unbuilt 'parallel roads': New York & Connecticut Eastern R.R.; New York & Connecticut Railway; New York & Connecticut Air Line R.R.; New York, Bridgeport & Eastern Railway.
  - Boston & New York Air Line R.R., 1873 May 6 - 1911 July 17 (Volume 12)
  - Miscellaneous roads, 1877 March 29 - 1911 July 10 (Volume 13)
    Includes Branford Steam R.R., Colchester R.R., Meriden & Cromwell R.R., South Manchester R.R., East Granby & Suffield R.R., Rockville R.R.
  - Connecticut Central R.R., 1874 December 30 - 1891 May 25 (Volume 14)
  - Connecticut Valley R.R., 1874 June 17 - 1909 May 27 (Volume 15)
  - Connecticut Western R.R., 1874 September 21 - 1911 September 8 (Volume 16)
  - Danbury & Norwalk R.R., 1874 October 20 - 1911 March 9 (Volume 17)
  - Hartford, Providence & Fishkill R.R., 1874 June 23 - 1884 June 17 (Volume 18)
    Pages 1-48 and 179-181 cover the Hartford, Providence & Fishkill R.R. Pages 75-178 cover the projected 'parallel road' Hartford and Harlem R.R., 1883 May 4 - 1884 June 17.
  - Housatonic R.R., 1874 October 21 - 1911 September 8 (Volume 19)
  - Naugatuck R.R., 1874 October 16 - 1911 January 13 (Volume 20)
  - Naugatuck R.R., 1911 March 22 (Volume 21)
    11 pages only
  - New Canaan R.R., 1874 November 4 - 1911 May 9 (Volume 22)
    Pages 175-186 cover the projected road Ridgefield & New York R.R. Pages 300-313 cover the projected road Danbury amp; State Line Railway.
  - New Haven & Derby R.R., 1875 October 26 - 1910 December 9 (Volume 23)
  - New Haven & Northampton R.R., 1874 August 21 - 1911 July 17 (Volume 24)
  - New London Northern R.R., 1874 November 5 - 1911 April 27 (Volume 25)
  - New York & New England R.R., 1875 March 31 - 1884 December 13 (Volume 26)
  - New York & New England R.R., 1884 December 22 - 1890 October 10 (Volume 27)
  - New York & New England R.R., 1890 October 2 - 1901 February 13 (Volume 28)
  - New York & New England R.R., 1901 March 11 - 1911 August 9 (Volume 29)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., New York & New Haven Division, No. 1, 1874 September 8 - 1886 October 14 (Volume 30)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., New York & New Haven Division, No. 2, 1886 October 16 - 1892 October 5 (Volume 31)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., New York & New Haven Division, No. 3, 1892 October 3 - 1896 September 15 (Volume 32)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., New York & New Haven Division, No. 4, 1896 September 29 - 1911 September 8 (Volume 33)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., Hartford & New Haven Division, No. 1, 1874 September 12 - 1888 April 14 (Volume 34)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., Hartford & New Haven Division, No. 2, 1888 April 28 - 1910 November 7 (Volume 35)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., Hartford and New Haven Division, Volume 3, 1910 July 1 - 1911 July 24 (Volume 36)
    9 pages only
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., Shore Line Division, Volume 1, 1874 October 21 - 1903 June 25 (Volume 37)
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., Shore Line Division, Volume 2, 1905 January 4 - 1911 July 3 (Volume 38)
    46 pages only
  - N.Y., N.H. & H. R.R., New York, Providence and Boston R.R., Volume 1, 1874 October 24 - 1908 May 29 (Volume 39)
  - Norwich and Worcester R.R., Volume 1, 1874 November 5 - 1911 March 17 (Volume 40)
  - Shepaug R.R., 1874 October 16 - 1911 June 27 (Volume 41)
  - Street Railways, Volume 1, 1895 December 18 - 1904 September 28 (Volume 42)
  - Street Railways, Volume 2, 1904 October 13 - 1908 July 15 (Volume 43)
  - Street Railways, Volume 3, 1908 August 1 - 1911 August 19 (Volume 44)
- Series 2. Correspondence, 1869-1911; 8.5 cubic feet; 1932-074
  - 1869 December - 1874 December (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
  - 1875 January - 1876 January (Box 2, Folder 1-12)
  - 1876 February - December 16 (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
  - 1876 December 16 - 1878 February (Box 4, Folder 1-12)
  - 1878 March - 1880 February (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
  - 1880 March - 1882 July (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
  - 1882 August - 1883 July 14 (Box 7, Folder 1-12)
  - 1883 July 16 - 1884 April (Box 8, Folder 1-12)
  - 1884 May - 1885 December (Box 9, Folder 1-12)
  - 1886 January - 1887 September (Box 10, Folder 1-12)
  - 1887 October - 1888 October (Box 11, Folder 1-12)
  - 1888 November - 1891 January (Box 12, Folder 1-12)
  - 1891 February - 1892 January (Box 13, Folder 1-12)
  - 1892 February - November 18 (Box 14, Folder 1-12)
  - 1892 November 19 - 1894 August (Box 15, Folder 1-12)
  - 1894 September - 1904 (Box 16, Folder 1-12)
  - 1905-1911 (Box 17, Folder 1-12)
- Series 3. Railroad Papers, circa 1848-1911, bulk 1860-1911; 19.25 cubic feet; 1932-074
  - Boston & New York Airline R.R., 1875-1911 (Box 18, Folder 1-8)
    Includes Colchester R.R.
  - Boston, Hartford & Erie R.R., 1864-1870 (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
  - Branford Steam R.R. Co., 1904-1910 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Includes Damascus R.R.
  - Connecticut Central R.R., 1869-1885 (Box 19, Folder 2-6)
  - Danbury & Norwalk R.R., 1861-1893 (Box 19, Folder 7-10)
  - Danbury & Norwalk R.R., 1894-1909 (Box 20, Folder 1-4)
  - East Granby & Suffield R.R., 1901-1902 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Hartford & Connecticut Valley R.R., 1870-1873 (Box 20, Folder 6-9)
  - Hartford & Connecticut Valley R.R., 1874-1911 (Box 21, Folder 1-10)
  - Hartford & Connecticut Western R.R., 1869-1897 (Box 22, Folder 1-9)
  - Hartford & Connecticut Western R.R., 1898-1911 (Box 23, Folder 1-7)
    Hartford & Connecticut Western R.R. papers in Boxes 22 and 23 include the Connecticut Western R.R., the Central New England & Western R.R., the Philadelphia, Reading & New England R.R. and the Central New England Railway
  - Hartford & New Haven R.R., 1857-1868 (Box 23, Folder 8-10)
    The Hartford & New Haven R.R.. papers in boxes 23-27 include the Union Branch R.R. (Hartford), Middletown R.R., Middletown Extension R.R., New Britain & Middletown R.R., Windsor Locks & Suffield R.R.
  - Hartford & New Haven R.R., 1869-1882 June (Box 24, Folder 1-9)
  - Hartford & New Haven R.R., 1882 July-1895 (Box 25, Folder 1-8)
  - Hartford & New Haven R.R., 1896-1910 (Box 26, Folder 1-9)
  - Hartford & New Haven R.R., 1911 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - Hartford, Providence & Fishkill R.R., 1859-1878 (Box 27, Folder 3-10)
  - Housatonic R.R., 1861-1895 (Box 28, Folder 1-10)
    Includes one New York, Housatonic & Northern R.R. item, September 22, 1871 in folder 2
  - Housatonic R.R., 1899-1911 (Box 29, Folder 1-6)
  - Housatonic R.R.: financial and legal documents, 1882 (Box 29, Folder 7-9)
  - Meriden, Waterbury & Connecticut River R.R., 1882-1910 (Box 30, Folder 1-6)
    Includes Meriden & Cromwell R.R., Meriden & Waterbury R.R., and Middletown, Meriden & Waterbury R.R.
  - Naugatuck R.R., circa 1848, 1863-1882 (Box 30, Folder 7-10)
    Includes Waterbury & Watertown R.R.
  - Naugatuck R.R., 1883-1905 (Box 31, Folder 1-9)
  - Naugatuck R.R., 1906-1911 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
  - New Canaan R.R., 1867-1872, 1908-1911 (Box 32, Folder 6-8)
  - New Haven & Derby R.R., 1867-1910 (Box 33, Folder 1-11)
  - New Haven & Northampton R.R., 1861-1903 (Box 34, Folder 1-10)
  - New Haven & Northampton R.R., 1904-1911 (Box 35, Folder 1-4)